in today's lesson i'm going to teach you
valley and overhead you know what valley
is
so valley is hit close to the net and
it's a shot that's taken in the air kind
of like volleyball
you know so if the ball bounces that's
considered a ground stroke okay
there's another thing called a half
volley but don't worry about that we'll
get to that later so i'm going to teach
you how to take the ball
out of the air when you're close to the
net you want to try a few
all right so you're standing right there
close to the net now i'm going to feed
you some balls go right in the middle
okay let me see okay that's pretty good
okay
actually you're doing really good
volleys you're doing a lot of things
already correct without ever having
uh played on these shots but one thing
that you're doing badly you're doing
what i call the windshield wiper so when
you get a ball on this side you hit it
like this
and when you get one on this side you're
going like this you know like a
windshield wiper on the car so the first
thing we have to change
we cannot hit volleys with a forehand
grip now you remember the backhand grip
that we used
yeah forehand is that remember backhand
turn your hand that way
and i point the racket towards me okay
let go the racket
and just put your hand on top right on
top like that there you go
that's called the continental grip and
the great thing about this grip is
you're gonna use it on your two-handed
backhand
on your volleys your overheads and all
the other kind of specialty shots that
you're going to be hitting
the only time you have to change your
grip is for the forehand so on the
valley it's very important that you use
the continental grip and now when the
ball comes on this side you're going to
use
one you change it to a forehand grip
okay so when a ball comes on this side
you're going to go like this
and you're basically going to do the
same thing you just did you're going to
deflect the ball back
you know what i mean by deflect it's
kind of like block
you basically let the ball let the ball
bounce off the strings and come back now
when it comes to the backhand you can
use the other hand to support eventually
it might be better off if you did just
one hand but you have to use the other
side of the racket you see so
you're using this side of the racket on
the backhand valley now let go
and using this side of the racket on the
forehand valley right and in the middle
you're in a ready position like this
okay and so here also just just deflect
yes block it for now no force no force
okay just let the ball bounce off the
strings let's see what happens okay now
i'm gonna feed it really gently you're
gonna go back into my hands okay
here we go forehand first
now what i'd like you to do is just set
the racket right away that way we don't
have to do it out of the ready position
and i keep your elbow in front like this
and now i'm going to throw the ball
you're just going to let it
deflect off your racket and come back to
me put it right there right away
put the elbow in front a little bit yeah
and you can keep the racket closer to
your body it's going to feel better
there
okay okay and just come back to me there
it is
okay not bad good come again
now you have a tendency not just you but
players in general have a tendency to
start straightening the arm
and it becomes more difficult when the
ball is further away so keep the arm
bent
but just get the elbow in front of the
body see the body here yeah you don't
want anything between here okay
like this and just deflect it back okay
nice ah you change your grip to a
forehand go back to continental
i noticed everything i'm watching you
very closely
good come again good again
nice all right now do backhand side
back inside you don't change the grip
you keep the elbow in front don't turn
too much stay a little more open like
this
okay a little bit like a little bit more
turn there you go perfect it's like a
quarter turn okay
and you come back to me okay if you go
like this if you snap the wrist a little
bit
it's going to go crooked there you go
that's good
good again nice
just deflect okay again it's all right
another one good again
good good
good nice and straighten the racket now
you already see how
how directional control works in tennis
if you make contact like this
you notice the balls are going crooked
right so if you want the ball to go
straight you got to keep the racket
straight okay
you have to break the wrist you have to
extend the wrist backwards
on this side it's going to be your left
hand on the forehand side is going to be
the right hand
okay
here we go okay that went up a little
bit maybe close the racket face slightly
good okay now go in the middle we'll try
forehand and backhand okay
so the ready position is going to be
slightly down with the upper body go
down a little bit a little bit more
there you go and get in your knees a
little bit bend your knees and get on
your toes
like that now the ball's going to come
you go forehand here one hand remember
and then back to the ready position and
back in here it's important to be really
ready at the net because the ball is
going to be coming fast
you don't have a lot of time because
you're close to the net
not completely on the toes like you know
like this but but a little bit more with
the weight forward
yeah here we go and again backhand
good forehand come good backhand
nice forehand and try to minimize the
movements of the racket you just deflect
the ball back in other words you block
it back
you let the ball play the racket good
come again
nice okay now i want to try something
because there is a disadvantage to
having a two-handed volley it's not
wrong to do two hands on this side
but you know volley oh well bali i'm not
saying it right it's
v-o-l-l-e-y okay
how do you say it volley volley we're
both saying it's wrong
it's actually volley with an o now go
ahead and put the rack on the side see
there's less reach
let's go with the left hand let go left
hand see now you have more reach with
one hand yeah
so it's an advantage to do one-handed
backhand volleys even though yeah
even though you have a two-handed
backhand back there so let me try that
real quick so go ahead and do with one
hand
let go of the left hand let me see what
that looks like
if you're strong enough you might be
able to do this right away
does that feel weak yeah yeah most
players are a little bit weak with their
wrist
when it comes to the uh one-handed
backhand volley so
what i recommend now maybe we add this
later
as you play more tennis but for now
we'll stick to the two-hander
and we'll change it down the road okay
and forehand
good backhand good
wow what do you think easy right yeah
okay let's make it harder oh no stand
behind this cone right here i'm going to
feed you short
you're going to run up with the rom
already set up like we practiced you're
going to put the elbow in front
you know keep the racket here the wrist
is going to be bent back you're going to
run up and then just deflect alright
ready
forehand come you're going to have to
run fast because the ball
is going to be very slow so the first
two or three steps are very explosive
and then kind of slow down closer to the
ball okay
fast go go go go go good
don't take your racket back like this
keep your racket in front like this
that's all you got to do just deflect
good job
good and go come get up there nice one
yes
let's try backhand same thing set the
racket already on that side
and you're gonna go this way come
come forward come get good come come
come come
what's happening is you're not uh you're
not moving through the ball
you're stopping too early and then
you're reaching like this yeah i'm not
sure where i am
just kissing to the ball i know just
keep going okay you got to try to get as
close to the net as possible
angle much better see that extra one or
two steps afterwards helps you to keep
the balance
angle good remember you shouldn't try to
extend the arms like this keep the
elbows a little bit closer to your body
it's going to give you a better feel
huh very nice all right now let's do
forehand and backhand so do
one forehand come back there ready
position and then backhand forehand
good backhand good forehand
nice and backhand side come on
good so you already learned how to
volley from a stationary position
and you learn how to volley moving
forward it was really good job but now
don't be scared but i'm going to hit the
ball harder to you and you're just going
to stand here and you're going to
deflect the ball back because that's the
reality when you come to the net people
are going to probably hit it a little
bit harder than i was
just now
good good
don't swing see what happens if you
swing you lose control immediately
that's why it's important to just
freeze the racket okay block the ball
good nice
nice good job how was that was that
scary
yeah right so if you are into that ready
position if you
keep your elbows in front it makes it a
lot easier to react so you have to
remember to be ready at the net you feel
like standing straight up
then it's even more difficult to react
yeah all right so one more thing we do
on the bali is what happens when you get
a low ball and now this turns really
into a very athletic type of volley
where you have to try to bend because
what you don't want to do
is keep your legs straight and bend the
upper body because now you'll volley up
so when you get a low volume you have to
go into a lunge you know what i mean by
lunge
and then you have to get the body down
so that the racket head doesn't drop too
low
but the racket head remains level and
then you can still hit a quality valley
so back up a little bit try to get as
low as possible
wow very good do it again ready position
and launch nice and again lunge
good again lunch wow okay now backhand
same thing okay
ready position and you're gonna lunge
and get as low as you can
oh you went a little bit down with the
upper body there here we go
not on the back and it's gonna be more
difficult the more natural weight is to
do it with your right leg
try it try one with your right leg try
you see it's more difficult
yeah with the left do it with the right
with the dominant leg now go ahead and
ready position
nice if you remember on our back end
lesson you also wanted to hit all your
two-handed backhands like this remember
so you have some kind of natural
preference to do it off this leg
you have to break that and do it the
other way around you have to
it feels kind of straight so yeah on the
left side use your right leg okay
do it again ready position better
yes yes you see now you get better
angles to work with a really good job on
the valley but now what do you do when
you're at the net and somebody gives you
like a high ball right
nice green okay you have to do something
called
an overhead so this shot is kind of
self-explanatory and what i noticed when
we were doing overheads in the beginning
okay try again another one
just like the serve you have the
tendency to be open towards the ball so
you see a ball
and this feels very safe to beginners to
kind of face the ball and do a shot like
this
so you have to break this natural habit
that you have
and turn sideways just like you did on
the serve so go standing right on this
line the ball is going to be coming high
as soon as you see it's high it's over
your head you're going to turn like this
and put the racket in the trophy
remember the trophy
right remember same grip still it's the
continental grip you're going to be
right here to get this
tilt of the shoulders you put your left
arm up towards the sky and now you see
your your chin is going to go over your
shoulder
you're going to be staring at the ball
with your chin over the left shoulder
like this so you need a full turn like
this racket is down on this side
left arm is up that's your ready
position for the overhead when the ball
is very close that's when you take a
swing at it and you're going to swing
down on it you're going to hit it hard
into the ground over the net of course
okay the mistake that you're doing is
very common so what i told you before
you're very comfortable opening up
so now you're setting up like this but
then you're opening up too early and
waiting for the ball like this
i want you to really wait like this it's
going to be really weird
wait like this until the ball is very
close and then when you accelerate
you're actually going to rotate into the
obviously you're not going to hit it
like this
you're going to rotate into the ball
like that okay okay
go ahead and get set
go again
okay better so first of all you're doing
a really good job on your overhead but
one mistake
you're still going too early like this i
want you to look where i'm accelerating
from on the overhead look
see my racket is in the trophy right
yeah i look here
you see how it's accelerating from here
look you can't see it because it's
accelerating fast so you're doing this
watch
right here you see how the racket is
waiting here
don't wait like this accelerate from
here look
so you're doing it because you want to
make sure that you make contact with the
ball so you put the strings flat like
this
because you mentally the image is like
the strings out towards the ball
and you know you're going to make
contact but if you wait here you're
going to accelerate
much longer and much faster therefore
your range of motion is going to
increase
so your racket's going to go in here out
here and then into the contact
better better
again best one so far
wow yes okay now we're gonna do the
ultimate test
uh we're gonna do everything we did
today a forehand valley a back and
valley and then an overhead
forehand good backhand
overhead
much better all right let's do a racket
tap
awesome awesome job